<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: novices | Danielle.A]]></title>
  <link href="http://dmarvanitis.github.io/blog/categories/novices/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://dmarvanitis.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2013-11-07T21:29:44-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://dmarvanitis.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Danielle Arvanitis]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[In mobile app design, do affordances still matter?]]></title>
    <link href="http://dmarvanitis.github.io/blog/affordances/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-28T15:14:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://dmarvanitis.github.io/blog/affordances</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Something I hear from novice mobile designers lately is that affordances “aren&rsquo;t needed anymore” because “users will just play with the app and figure things out.” When pressed by more senior members of a UX team, these designers often suggest making up for the missing affordance by highlighting the feature in a tutorial or displaying a screen overlay with tips on how to use the app.</p>

<p>Here are just some of the problems with that thinking.</p>

<h1>Experimentation and reading require time that your users don&rsquo;t have</h1>

<p>In Fall of 2012 I piloted a study for my employer, Good Technology. Good makes apps for Android, iOS, and Windows Phone that let a company’s employees collaborate securely from wherever they happen to be throughout the day. I wanted to see how well our products supported senior executives, whose needs typically differ from those of the rank and file.</p>

<p>I was shocked at what I found. Our own big shots—the people with the highest compensation, the most stock options, and ultimately the most to gain from our company’s success—weren’t using our apps.</p>

<p>“I don&rsquo;t have time to set up the apps,” one admitted. &ldquo;I get to configuration and think, &lsquo;I don&rsquo;t have time for this right now. I&rsquo;ll come back to it later.&rsquo;&rdquo;</p>

<p>“I never spent the time to learn it,” another said sheepishly. &ldquo;I&rsquo;m sure it would work, but I&rsquo;ve just never tried it.&rdquo;</p>

<p>It was hard to believe, but these executives were too busy for apps that could not only help them with their day-to-day work, but were the same apps upon which their own livelihoods depended.</p>

<p>In case you&rsquo;re tempted to consider these executives outliers, even &ldquo;average&rdquo; users are becoming famous for <a href="http://usatoday30.usatoday.com/MONEY/usaedition/2012-01-31-App-Love-is-Fleeting_ST_U.htm">trying an app once or twice and then deleting it</a>. App creators have a <a href="http://www.nuance.com/ucmprod/groups/enterprise/@web-enus/documents/collateral/nc_020218.pdf">very short window</a> in which to hook potential users. Discovering hidden features and reading tutorials require a time commitment that a tiny fraction of your potential user base is willing to make.</p>

<p>The bottom line? Don&rsquo;t assume that <em>anyone</em> wants to invest time in your app.</p>

<h1>Missing affordance means missing feature</h1>

<p>As part of the same study, I interviewed an executive assistant who supported the Chief Revenue Officer. She was frustrated that there was no setting for the number of message-preview lines for the emails in her Inbox.</p>

<p>“Yes, there is,” I said. I had an inkling of what was going on, but I played dumb. “You didn’t find it?”</p>

<p>“No,” she said, and looked again at the app on her phone.</p>

<p>“Do you see a way to find Preferences?” I asked.</p>

<p>“Preferences? There aren&rsquo;t any!” she said.</p>

<p>The tab bar across the bottom of her iPhone screen contained icons for Email, Calendar, Contacts, Tasks, and Documents. I reached over and swiped the bar from right to left. Suddenly, icons for Browser, Applications, and Preferences slid into view. She gasped.</p>

<p>Clearly, she hadn&rsquo;t read the tutorial.</p>

<p><img src="http://dmarvanitis.github.io/../images/blogImages/navbar.png" alt="screenshot" title="Oops" /></p>

<p>I could only be embarrassed for the UX team, because I knew the story behind the error. The lead designer hadn’t wanted to add an affordance for swiping the tab bar, and management had backed him on it. Some of us knew that some users would never discover the swipe—but we didn&rsquo;t know there would be one just down the hall who was responsible for supporting our own Chief Revenue Officer.</p>

<h1>Missing or “surprise” features result in annoyed users</h1>

<p>I won’t forget one IT Director I spoke to during a usability test. He was trying to perform a task using the native iPhone calendar, and as he turned to show me the screen, the phone’s orientation rotated to landscape. Suddenly, he found himself looking at the calendar’s week view.</p>

<p>“What’s this?” he asked, startled.</p>

<p>From the tone of his voice I could guess what he was thinking, but I wanted to demonstrate his reaction to my team, who were observing the test from another room. “It&rsquo;s week view,” I said. “You just turn the phone sideways, and…voilà!”</p>

<p>A storm cloud passed over his face. “<em>Week view?</em> Do you know how much time this could have saved me if I’d known about it? And it’s been here all this time?”</p>

<p>He was irate. iOS 5 had been out for months, but with no affordances to go on, he’d had no idea that week view existed. He lost some faith in Apple that day.</p>

<h1>Yes—affordances matter</h1>

<p>If you think users don’t need affordances because they can learn to use your app by playing around with it or by reading a tutorial or hints screen, think again. Most people are too busy to spend time getting acquainted with your baby. They’ll jump right in, skip tips, and miss important features—and some of them won&rsquo;t forgive you for having wasted their time.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
