<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: quality | Danielle.A]]></title>
  <link href="http://dmarvanitis.github.io/blog/categories/quality/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://dmarvanitis.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2013-11-09T12:11:23-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://dmarvanitis.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Danielle Arvanitis]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Some numbers to keep in mind while designing]]></title>
    <link href="http://dmarvanitis.github.io/blog/number/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-28T15:14:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://dmarvanitis.github.io/blog/number</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>There’s an old saying that goes, “The only numbers developers care about are 0, 1, and N.”
Sounds like the punch line to a bad joke, right? But what it means is that developers have
to make sure their code accounts for those numbers.</p>

<p>Once I heard this saying, and the reason for it, I tried to remember those numbers when I was designing. For example:</p>

<ul>
<li><p><strong>0.</strong> How does my design handle 0 of something? What does it look like if there are no items in my container, whether it’s an email folder, a to-do list, a list of chats? Is there anything special my app or site needs to do to indicate or handle this 0 of something? How am I going to do it?</p></li>
<li><p><strong>1.</strong> What does 1 of something look like? Are there any special cases related to having only 1 of something?</p></li>
<li><p><strong>N.</strong> N isn’t always so easy. It could be anything from 3 to 300, or even 3,000. How will my design accommodate N of something?
As it turns out, there are other special numbers when it comes to UX design. One of them is the number 2, as I recently noticed while using Twitter for iPhone.</p></li>
</ul>


<p>I have two Twitter accounts, and sometimes I switch between them to tweet different types of things.</p>

<p>Here’s what my main account’s profile looks like. If I tap the “Accounts” button, I get a list of my accounts.</p>

<p><img src="http://dmarvanitis.github.io/../images/blogImages/numbers_screenshots.png" alt="screenshots" title="Button
doesn’t toggle between two accounts" /></p>

<p>To switch, I tap the button, pick my other account, and wait for the window to close.</p>

<p>But wait. I only have <em>two</em> accounts. Why, when I tap this button, should I have to see a list of accounts and manually select my other account? When I have two accounts configured, Twitter should just swap them. That button should just <em>toggle</em> between my two accounts. The number 2 is a special case.</p>

<p>So, some numbers to keep in mind while you’re designing: 0, 1, 2, and N. And there could be others, depending on the domain and tasks you’re trying to accommodate. You might want to add them to a design checklist before your next design review.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
